Hello and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan and today we're
going to be further looking at how to
prepare for your Chem 3A ACS final.
So in this particular video, I'm going
to go through the exact topics that
you need to review for your exam.
So we're going to go chapter by chapter
and I'm going to talk about which concepts
you need to know how to calculate and
which concepts you need to know the theory
behind in order to succeed on your test.
If you study each of these concepts,
you will most likely be able to score
anywhere from an A to a B, but only
if you do spend the time to go through
them and to review them very, very well.
So I would recommend that being
this as your final exam, if you are
counting on this test, you need to
spend the time to study every single
chapter, at least to an extent.
Um, usually when it comes to reviewing
for this type of exam, you will You
probably will have to study anywhere
from four to eight hours of your
time to really be able to review it.
You could go through all my review videos
on it, which would be a start, but the
big thing is making sure you go through
all the different problems to master this.
Now, if you haven't seen what the format
of this test is, please go to part one.
And if you want to know what these
types of problems look like, refer
to Part 3 or maybe Part 4 or beyond,
depending on how many I decide to make,
which will go through example problems
and how we can actually break down and
to succeed at these types of tests.
Okay, let's take a look.
The
first chapter was all about
measurements and dimensional analysis.
In my course, we focus for the first like
couple weeks of the class really just
focusing on, can you do calculations?
Do you know your math basics?
And now when you're going through
this, what you're going to, the way
I'm going to kind of situate all
these different chapters is telling
you what you need to calculate.
and what theory you need to know in terms
of how to answer a theoretical question.
So when it comes to the calculations,
most of these come down to can you
convert units and can you do just
simple word problems on how to
convert from one thing or to another.
So for example, one of the first things
that you did a lot of conversions
with was the concept of density.
So you will have to do
density driven calculations.
So make sure you remember that, hey,
that's grams over milliliter or, um,
kilograms over liter or, uh, kilograms
over milliliter, knowing that's
always a mass over a volume when you
were doing those different amounts.
The other thing that you will have
to know is how to take approximations
based on info given, right?
There might be multiple problems in a row
that might all have to do with each other.
Okay.
And they might be about similar concepts.
So can you do approximations
based on that?
Now after that, there's
also sig figs, right?
So do you remember your basic
sig figs rules all semester long?
You've had this drilled in your brain
between whether it's your homework,
your quizzes, your exams, your lab
reports, between my open math and
doing the different assignments,
you have had to do sig figs.
So you shouldn't know them
better than anything else.
Better hope for 60 sig fig
questions because you'll
hopefully get them all correct.
There's also temperature.
Um, so you need to know how to
go from Kelvin to Celsius, right?
So all the different SI units
when you're going through that.
Now the other concept that you need to
know as well is when it comes to the
theory is about the scientific method.
So do you know the difference between what
a law is a hypothesis experiment theory?
And if you're like, Oh, I
don't remember any of those.
Go back and review them.
They're in your notes from probably
the first week of the class.
Review them, see what they
are, just so you remember.
Um, atoms.
So when it comes to discovery, it
was more like, how were the protons
founded, neutrons, electrons.
Knowing those little basic
techniques of how we came to know
that we had positive particles,
negative particles, and neutral.
So knowing those basic ideas.
Now when it comes to calculations, this
all had to just do with counting, so can
you count how many protons, neutrons,
electrons there were, and a lot of this
came from your periodic table, right?
So if you have, let's say, uh, the
atom, let's say helium for example,
and above it, it had the number 2, and
then below it, it had the number 4.
008 underneath of it, do you know what all
those different pieces represent, right?
So, When we're looking at them, we
know, Hey, this is your atomic mass.
We have our atomic number above it.
And then we know, all right, the atomic
number represents the number of protons.
Whereas the atomic mass
is protons plus neutrons.
So you can kind of do some simple
little, um, calculations to
figure out which one is each.
And we'll go through this a lot
in different videos as well.
And then how to calculate
your charges, right?
Remember, atoms are inherently neutral.
And ions, when it came to cations and
anions, had more or less electrons,
which a lot of that was covered in
Chapter 3, so let's look at that.
But when it came to essentially Chapter
3, this was all about all the different
atoms, which groups are they in, and
what came to how we can count electrons.
So the first thing really is, well, do you
know how the periodic tables organized?
Which mainly had to tell you that,
okay, they were in groups, they were
known as alkali metals, alkaline
metals, halogens, transition metals.
Noble gases, just to name some of them,
right, so you had the metal section,
the non metal section, and that is
like your theory part, can you name the
groups, can you situate where they're at.
Um, when it came to calculations,
could you count how many valence
electrons there are, right?
Earlier I showed you a periodic table
and I showed you a trick on how to
count valence electrons, I showed
you that in previous videos as well.
Um, can you count just the regular amount
of electrons when it comes to a neutral.
or a cation or an anion, right?
If you see a positive charge,
that means less electrons.
If you see a negative charge,
that means more electrons.
Can you count them?
Can you also do electron configuration?
And that might be, you know, 1s2, 2s2,
2p6, so forth, which you're like, Oh my
God, I haven't thought of that in forever.
Well, these are things that you need to
review and try to make sure you understand
so that way you're not gonna call with
it Um, generally in this test luckily,
there's no real like quantum mechanics
calculations So it's very rare that you'll
ever see like an energy calculation or
a light calculation It's all about can
you organize your electrons and be able
to understand how the atom essentially
is labeled Let's look at chapter four.
Chapter four is all about
compounds and bonding.
So now that we have our electrons
that are going to either be shared or
taken, right, you have to know when
it's covalent or when it's ionic.
Covalent is when you have non metals
together that are sharing electrons.
Ionic is when you have a, generally have
a cation and an anion, and then the cation
is mainly a metal or ammonium, right?
Those are the only two.
So, if you have a cation, it will
give its electron to the anion.
You need to be able to swap, drop,
and balance charges, so if you don't
remember what I'm talking about there,
so if you think like, okay, I have
barium two plus, I can get that from
the periodic table, and C minus, I could
swap, drop their charges, and be able
to see that, oh, I have B A C L 2 as
my molecule, right, barium chloride.
Now, the other thing is as well as
you need to be able to name them too.
So I'd recommend remembering
your naming principles.
Um, also when you're going through
things like, uh, Let's say if I have iron
three chloride as a name, knowing that
the Roman numerals represent charges.
Okay.
So if I have F E, that'd be F E for iron.
And then that means it's a three plus
charge when I am looking at this, right?
So it'd be F E, we'd swap, drop it,
and then make it F E C L three when
we're looking at all how to figure
out all those different things.
The roman numeral is a
charge, not a subscript, okay?
So please, please, please remember
that when you are doing this exam.
Now for chapter five, this was moles
and then chemical formulas again.
So the big thing is this is mainly
calculations, like can you calculate
molar mass, you know, by adding up
all the different molar masses from
your periodic table and then be able
to use a subscript to calculate that.
And then when it comes to your
calculations, can you figure out how many
moles there are within a formula, right?
So for example, if I had, um, let's say
I had calcium, uh, phosphate, right?
And I were to look at this molecule and
I asked you, well, how many of each, how
many moles of each thing do I have here?
Well, I could tell you from the
subscripts, and this is something that
you could count is I have three moles
of calcium, two plus, I have 2 moles
of phosphorus that's here, and then
I have 8 moles of oxygen, and that's
by multiplying out those different
pieces, so that way you know, ooh,
how to do the different conversions.
Now when you put all these in,
they are all equivalent to 1 mole
of calcium 3 phosphate, right,
which is our molecule here.
So there are many different relationships
that you can get from moles.
and from counting.
Now from there, we had chapter
six, which is all on the molecular
shape, electronegativity,
polarity, intermolecular forces.
These were all very, very conceptual
concepts, mainly revolving around theory.
Now, what do you need to know?
So being that this was a little bit
more of an involved chapter, it had a
huge part, we did an entire lab on this.
The one thing that you really need to
make sure you're comfortable with is
how to predict the number of bonds.
That, um, element forms, right?
Halogens are always one bond.
So a little trend to
remember for yourself.
So if you remember your periodic table,
right, we have fluorine, oxygen, nitrogen,
carbon on the periodic table when it
comes to the number of bonds, right?
Fluorine always does one.
Oxygen does two, nitrogen does three,
carbon does four individual bonds.
Knowing that trend can
be very, very beneficial.
Knowing how to write your different
Lewis structures, right, can you, based
on the knowing the number of bonds,
can you draw a simple Lewis structure?
And keep in mind this is
multiple choice, right?
So the thing is, if you know
your bonding trend, you probably
will get the correct answer.
Um, can resonant structure?
Which, what that means is, let's say
if I had a, Uh, one of the following
molecules, let's say I had carbonate,
for example, just kind of coming up on,
on top of my head, and we were to fill
in all of the lone pairs that are here.
Well, resonance structure tells me
how many other possibilities that
you can have for this molecule.
Well, the thing is, well, we have the
double bond here on the top molecule.
Could it move to maybe one of the left
or the right structure as a possibility?
And the answer is, yeah, sure.
So why don't I switch it to the side here?
And what we'll do is, is we'll fill in,
so we put our oxygen in, our carbon,
our single bonded carbon, and we'll move
the single bond and the double bond.
So here we have another option.
Now is that everything?
Well, what's preventing me from doing
the same thing where let's say I put the
double bond on the right hand side this
time, and I put it on the other part.
So how many resonance
structures do I have this time?
Well, I have a total of three
possible resonance structures.
So that's usually all you have to do
is count how many different possible
structures can the double bond switch to.
So we can see we have three, um, when it
comes to polar and nonpolar, this mainly
has to do with, can you see our, if you
have the same atom, they cancel out and
does it follow what geometry does it
follow if it's the basic geometry and
the same atoms all around the central.
Okay.
Cool.
then it's going to be considered nonpolar.
Just for the purposes of this test,
in order to see if it's polar is if
there are lone pair electrons around
the central atom, then it is polar.
Okay, just to make it easier for yourself.
So for example, something like
that is let's say I have ammonium,
which has a lone pair on it.
This is something that would be polar,
because we have those lone electrons on
the nitrogen, versus all the hydrogens
that are surrounding on all sides.
Now we also need to know
our intermolecular forces.
So does it have, uh, hydrogen bonding,
dipole dipole dispersion, and you need
to remember those different forces.
Chapter 7.
Chapter 7 was all about mainly knowing
your calculations, so when it comes to
heat, So, your MCAT equation, that's
the only thing that you'll have to
calculate, so can you solve for any of
the different variables, whether it's
Q for heat, M for mass, or the change
in temperature, which is delta T.
Remember, this is one of the formulas
that you need to know off the top of your
head, so remember the MCAT equation, and
then keep in mind that specific heat can
be in both joules per grams per Celsius,
or in calories per gram per Celsius.
Realize, though, that it's
Celsius, too, so look at the
units that are given to you.
It gives you a lot of hints
that are in the problem.
In terms of theory, you have to
know, like, what properties does
a solid, liquid, and a gas have,
and that has to refer to, like,
what's its shape and its volume.
Is it definite or is it indefinite?
So, like, a solid has a definite
volume, a definite shape.
Volume generally has a definite
volume, indefinite shape, because it
can take the shape of any container.
From there, knowing how phase changes.
These changes are referred to as
physical changes, meaning that
when that happens, you do not
break it down into anything else.
So if you were to freeze water,
it, it hardens and turns into
ice, but it's still water, right?
It's just a water in solid form.
If you boil water, it's going to
turn, it's going to start bubbling.
And those bubbles,
right, are water, right?
Steam starts coming off.
This is a physical change.
Um, when it comes to exothermic
or endothermic, realizing
how heat is transferred.
So is it something that's
absorbed from a system?
Does it come off from it?
If it feels colder, it's absorbing it.
If it's something that feels
hotter, it's releasing it.
So let's take a look at our next part.
So in chapter 8, what we
learned about was gases.
So with, when it comes to gases,
it's mainly calculation focused.
Now the good thing is, is uh, there's,
you really only need to know two gas
laws when it comes to solving anything
when it comes to gases, and it has
to do with either the ideal gas law.
or the combined gas law.
So the first thing is, well,
when do you know to use both?
This was an entire thing that I covered
in many other videos, so I'd recommend
reviewing the gas laws if you need help.
And it has to do with whether or not
there's no change, or if there is change.
Now, how can you tell?
Well, if there is change in the
system, then it has multiple pressures
listed, multiple volumes, multiple
temperatures, multiple moles.
No change lists.
One variable for each.
For each thing.
So like one pressure, one volume, one mos
when you're going through the calculation.
So if there is change, you
gotta use combined gas law.
If there isn't, then you want to use
the ideal gas law if fully depends
on which type of problem you have.
And then when it comes to the combined
gas law, if you have anything that's
constant, you can remove that variable.
So, for example, if I had temperature and
moles, they were constant, so what you can
actually do is we can erase essentially
everything that's on the bottom.
And then you'll notice that, hey, we
now have Boyle's law because temperature
and, uh, moles were held constant.
Whenever something is
constant, it can go away.
So keep that in mind when you're
looking at these problems.
The terms of theory, it's
mainly the conceptual thing.
So like, do you know how the gases
will behave if another one is changing?
So we did these examples a lot in class.
So for example, if.
volume is increasing,
pressure is decreasing.
So a lot of this you can actually get
from the formula from the ideal gas law.
So if you know how to kind of do,
to use this thing, you can, you can
do a lot of simple little tricks.
So one thing is, let's say if I wanted to
see, how does volume and pressure change?
Well, let's say for example,
if the pressure is doubled,
what happens to the volume.
So what you can actually do is, is we
can make some little assumptions here
and plug in some like fake numbers.
So let's say if the volume was doubled,
so I have one atmosphere on one side,
two atmospheres on the other, and I
want to know what happens to a volume.
So why don't we make it really easy
and we'll say we have one liter.
So what, what's the new volume?
What can we do is we can essentially just
rearrange our problem And what you'll see
is that well, when I move two atmospheres
to the left, you have one divided by
two, which means it's equal to one half.
So your new volume is one half of your
original volume, which was one liter.
So when you double pressure, you're
going to be having your volume.
So as pressure increases,
volume decreases.
There are little trends that you can
try to solve when you're going through
these, when you're trying to do the
math to see like, all right, well,
I don't know what's going to happen.
I don't know how to guess it.
Just come up with a simple number
to be able to explain when the
concept plugging into the formula.
It's a trick that I've been
using for a very long time
in order to understand math.
Now, when it comes to chapter nine.
This also has to do with solutions.
So solutions, there was a lot of
things that we did, we did multiple
labs on how to do net ionic equations,
how to do solubility, how to do
molarity, and we drilled a lot of
these different things into your brain.
So the big thing is, is well, when it
comes to calculating molarity, Make
sure you're comfortable with getting
a, getting something into moles and
then dividing into liters, right?
If it starts as a mass,
can you convert to moles?
Can you divide it by the volume?
Knowing when to use the
dilution formula, right?
You got to look for that keyword, dilute.
If you see that, that means that that
is the formula that you have to use, but
it's up to you to be able to recognize it.
Now when it comes to concentration
solutions, The biggest ones actually
have to do with the following,
which is mass over volume.
Versus weight over volume, right?
So if you see an M that refers
to mass, W means weight.
Which, like wait, what's
the difference between them?
There, frankly, is not a
difference between the two.
They are used interchangeably
in the health field.
Which is one of the reasons why it's so
focused on in this test because many of
you want to become healthcare workers.
So this test is geared at you.
So when it comes to these is realizing
that it's always referring to
grams of your solute all over 100
milliliters of your solution when we
are dealing with weight over volume.
So keep that in mind.
You'll also have to do
concentration of ions.
So if you're starting with, let's say
like this example up here, and I have,
um, one molar of copper hydroxide.
What does that mean is that if I do a
conversion here, and let's say this is
aqueous, just so we have, get rid of
our argument here, we will have a one
to one ratio based on the coefficients.
So you're going to have one, you
could convert that to be one mole
of copper, two moles of hydroxide
based on the coefficients, right?
When you do the mole to mole conversion.
So this is like kind of the
little things to keep in mind when
you're, when you're doing these.
And when it comes to theory.
There's quite a bit that
actually gets applied.
This is probably one of the bigger
chapters that gets tested on the most.
So this one might be a
really good one to focus on.
The first one is, can you, do you remember
your colligative properties, right?
So there's boiling point elevation,
osmotic pressure, and then freezing
point, or sorry, freezing point depression
and boiling point elevation in osmosis
were the three colligative properties.
Um, so knowing that with osmosis that,
um, you'll have a, Water will flow
into an area of high concentration
is an area is one really big one and
then knowing like hyper hypotonic
isotonic in hyper tonic solutions.
Um, mainly when it comes, I use
an example in my videos around red
blood cells, I would recommend going
back to the colligative property
video and reviewing that concept.
Um, being that this is, this
class does translate into
physio physiology and anatomy.
These concepts tend to be tested on
at least once in a lot of these exams.
Now, when it comes to solubility, the
big thing about this is, you don't,
you're not given your solubility
table, but you're never asked any type
of really weird solubility trends.
But really the biggest thing to
know is if you always remember
what is soluble, you'll be fine.
Which always was the abbreviation of AANA
when it comes to what is always soluble.
So it was always ammonium, acetate,
nitrate, and then the alkali
metals are what is always soluble.
So keep that in mind when
you are reviewing these.
Let's look at our next chapter.
Chapter 10 was all about
how chemical reactions work.
So the first thing is how to
balance a chemical reaction.
You need to know how to do that, right?
That is step one when it
comes to the chemistry course.
If you don't know how to do that,
then there's a, there's a good
chance you might not get the
grade you want in the end, right?
You need to know how to balance.
The other thing is, can you identify
the major types of reaction, right?
There's combination,
decomposition, combustion, double
replacement, single replacement.
There's five major types.
And that was something that we
talked about in a previous video,
types of chemical reactions.
And you identify.
When it comes to oxidation reduction,
really the only thing you're looking
at, looking for is, does the thing lose
electrons as in oxidation, or does it
gain electrons as in reduction, right?
Leo goes GERK, and you identify
loss and gain of electrons.
Um, when it comes to the net ionic
equations, the big thing is loss.
Solids and gases are what is
kept in the net ionic equation.
And you, the other thing is,
you know, what ions make it.
So like, for example, if we go up
to this problem here and we wanted
to kind of look at, well, how would
I show the net ionic equation?
Well, this here is a net ionic
equation because it's showing that
copper hydroxide broke down to
copper two plus copper hydroxide.
We kept the solid and
then we kept the ions.
that actually broke it up, right?
If you switch that, you would get
your standard net ionic equation.
Um, luckily there's not many
of those, but you still need
to be able to recognize them.
So look for those solids.
Now stoichiometry, this one
is a big calculation topic.
Um, big thing is I broke it
down into what you need to know.
Luckily it's not a ton.
Um, the first thing is, can you
do like a mole to mole conversion?
So can you read a chemical, a balanced
chemical equation and convert?
Can you do something like maybe
milligrams or kilograms to grams
to moles, so using your prefixes?
Can you do mass to mole
to mole to mass, right?
So using your chemical formula
again to do that, so that would be
like the step here in the middle.
Can you do that mole to mole
ratio, which is crucial?
And then can you do a
limiting reactant problem?
Now, keep in mind, this is
where, like, the tactfulness of
you taking your tests is key.
If you come across a limiting reagent
problem, meaning you're given the amounts
of two different species, this might be
one you want to come back to, because
it's something that's going to take you
potentially a few minutes to complete.
Remember, they're all worth the
same amount of points, so this could
be one you could go to later when
it comes to those points, um, when
you're going through all of them.
Let's look at chapter 12.
Chapter 12 is all about acids and bases.
So when it comes to calculating, the
one thing you need to be able to do
is calculate pH, which I should have
put this formula above, but pH is
equal to the negative log of H plus.
So this is the one other formula that you
need to know that I forgot to put above.
So, okay, there's one more.
So you need to do that one.
You need to be able to identify
a conjugate acid base pair.
Right.
So remember they differ by one proton.
Um, you need to be able to identify
your strong acids and bases.
So remember, acids always have H
plus at the beginning of the name.
So that is always an acid.
And then a base always has a
cat ion followed by hydroxide
at the end of the name.
So it has to be something
that's like usually a metal.
That's in front or something with a
positive charge when you're trying
to identify that other species.
You'll have to be able to interpret
the Ka's of acids and bases.
Remember, what does that mean is that the
stronger, the higher the Ka is, the more
it's over 1, the stronger the acid, the
lower that value is, the weaker the acid.
And when it comes to these, right,
strong acids, they completely
dissociate into all ions.
So this is K is greater than 1.
And when you have a weak acid, that means
that you'll still have some molecules
left over, and K1 will still be existing.
So like, here we have HA, you see
that they're still in solution.
Versus this other species, you
see that they're all broken
down into their individual ions.
So knowing the difference between the
two is really crucial to succeeding
on, on questions on this test.
Can you identify the differences?
Let's look at our last two chapters.
When it comes to equilibrium, and
then the final chapter, which is, um,
nuclear chemistry, the biggest thing
when it comes to equilibrium is, can
you interpret Le Chatelier's principle?
Meaning, like, do you know
how a reaction's gonna behave
when you imply a stress to it?
So, can you, do you know like some
key words like pushing a reaction to
completion, which means how do you
push the reaction forward or how do you
mainly keep it as reactants, which will
push the reaction backwards, right?
Can you figure out what
direction it's going?
Um, do you know how to increase the
concentration, decrease the concentration?
That's the only thing that you
really need to do with the theory.
There's not a ton when it comes to these.
So if you can know what those four
concepts do, which were concentration,
temperature, volume, and catalyst
can do, you will be completely fine.
So it's temperature, volume, pressure, and
then how does a catalyst behave, right?
So those are your, those are your
four concepts of what to look
for when we're, when we're trying
to answer this type of test.
Now when it comes to nuclear chem,
which is our last chapter, All's
we're going to be doing here is we
need to just balance, mainly balance
nuclear decay, which is the main thing.
So knowing how to balance like alpha,
beta, positron, gamma rays, can
you balance those equations, right?
It's the, you have to conserve mass.
So the atomic mass needs to
be the same on both sides.
The atomic number needs to
So can you do that for nuclear
decay and bombardment equations?
And then can you solve
a half life equation?
So could you, could you
do each of those things?
So those are all going
to be calculation based.
There's no theory with this one.
It's all calculation.
So being that this is also one of
the most recent things in the class,
hopefully this is one of the things
that you'll get really easily as well.
Um, so this has been every single
topic that is covered in our final.
I would recommend fully going over them
so that way you're familiar with them.
I hope, I know this probably wasn't
the most exciting video, but I wanted
to give you that complete rundown,
complete list of what to study when
you're going through your notes and
how to break them down by chapter.
Um, so I hope that this
helped you be able to do that.
Please come back for my next few videos,
which will be going through the different
problem sets and exactly what the thought
process is of how to go through them,
which will review a lot of the types of
problems that you're seeing here as well.
All right.
Thank you so much for coming by.
I hope that this video helped.
And I'll hope to see
you all in the future.
All right.
Bye now.